okay so thanks everybody for uh joining us
this week um for the magnet seminar uh today
i'm very pleased to say or just
a sorry reminder actually that
our seminars are 20 to 25 minutes uh kindly asks
that you uh keep your microphones muted and not
to interrupt the speaker if you are having
problems with your internet connection please
uh turn off your video that can help speed things
up and at the end of the presentation we'll have
a chance for a 10 to 15 minute uh question and
discussion session and you can we'll invite
you to mute your microphone to ask your questions
but you're welcome to type them into the chat and
one of myself or the other conveners will read
them out for you and at the end of the seminars
and we have chance for uh an informal catch
up and a bit of a a chin wag with everybody
um and that part of the seminar is is is um
not recorded so today i i'm really pleased to
win williams from um the university of
edinburgh and he will be talking to us about
um peter magnetic recording and whether or not i
apologize i've got the wrong title on the slide
it got me worried then i thought what do i know
about that well that's what happens when i don't
copy paste properly um so you'll be talking today
about micromagnetic models and what they can tell
us about uh paleomagnetic recording i'll pass
over to you and the proper title then great
okay let's hope i keep to time let me just
get my laser pointer working and laser pointer
okay
all right so uh let's start so um this talk is
going to describe a new model of thermo-magnetic
remnants in pseudoscience domain grains using
numerical micromagnetic models and it's been
a long time in development working with a whole
bunch of people you can see listed here uh
particularly with lesnar who has i've been working
with on this problem almost on a daily basis
and lisa talks who has been pushing us for
a long time to put our models to good use
so the talk is going to be divided into four
sections the first three sections being very
quick if i can make it so to get everything
finished in time um briefly i'm going to start
off by saying why we need numerical models then go
on to mention a few attempts of model verification
i've cut that section down to the bare minimum
uh so but at the end if you have any questions
got a whole bunch of dayplus forks and other
hysteresis there if you want to look at it
i will review our methodology of calculating
thermal stability and blocking temperatures
in pseudosignal domain grains before developing
that into a full trm model and simulating
multi-step telepathic intensity experiments in
a sample containing single vortex domain states
so this is where we're going to start uh it's
an important reminder that rocks are not simple
structures in terms of magnetic recording when the
when many of the magnetic recording models were
first put forward in the 1950s by
nail stone and woolforth and others
they produced a highly successful and for
the most part accurate theory that has been
verified countless times but in reality of
course their theories actually apply more to
structures like this these are non-interacting
uniformly magnetized very magnetic particles
and this particular image just take was
from a sample made by david crasser using
electron beam lithography some time ago
but i think it's pretty clear that these
samples to which single main theory applies
do not look like rocks rocks look like this
so if we can get this other one going oh
rotate it's not going to rotate there we go
rocks are much more complex with irregular
structures wide variety of grain sizes
and mineralogies so these are two remarkable
images reconstructed by the fib slice and view
technique to reveal distributions of iron oxides
inside the one on the right is from the work of
evan nicholason and on the left is some
work i'm doing with allison cowan and
adrian marksworthy at imperial college i think
what is clear and i think what is generally true
is that we do not have arrays of
non-interacting non-uniformly magnetized screens
and in fact if you take a closer look
of some of allison's data which i have
access to that she's given to me the last
few days we can identify numerous grains
of a highly irregular morphology and these
grain shapes and sizes have a profound impact
on the magnetic recording characteristics as
we will see shortly so of course the way to
understand these complex particle morphologies
and the complex magnetic structures they contain
are through micromagnetic modeling and here's
my plug for our open source micromagnetic
modeling software this was started by phil ridley
and myself many many years ago but significantly
upgraded by carl fabian paddy o'connor lesnar and
others it's a robust and efficient piece of code
that runs on anything from a cray to to an old
shoebox and those of you who might be interested
in playing around with this can download it from
rockman.org where there are also some tutorials
um so the i'm not going to show you how these
models work in detail except to say that it's
a finite element model so we start out by
creating a 3d model that's filled with tetrahedral
elements such as we show here we represent the
magnetization by unit vector at every node of
each element and then we solve the lowest energy
magnetic structures for that grain so here are
some local energy minimum solutions here we've
colored the magnetization according to uh in
this case according to the alignment with the
crystalline easy axis and we also often highlight
the vorticity by plotting the helicity iso surface
as you can see the generally the more complex the
shape the more complex is its magnetic structure
we've gone to great lengths to try and verify our
models and i'll show you just a couple of examples
this is a grain of magnetite along with this off
axis electron holographic image on the right hand
side uh in some work i did with trevor almeida
some years ago and on the left-hand side is our
reconstruction of the grain and the simulated
off-axis electron holographic image i think that
shows a remarkable resemblance to that of the real
grain uh some other work that i've done here is uh
with evenier caprova from the rm in minnesota who
produced these amazing magnetic force microscope
images of a large tm-54 grain it's about 1.4
microns or so in size the micromagnetic models
are shown on the right hand uh i'm sorry on the
top uh row and on the right hand corner and the
simulated mf images mfm images are on the middle
row and the experimentally observed mfm images are
on the bottom row and again i think there's very
good agreement between the simulated mfm images
from our predictive micromagnetic structures
and that that is observed experimentally
now uh at this point it's worth repeating
a very nice quote from george box whose
famous british statistician who said in one
of his papers that all models are wrong but
some are useful and i think that definitely
applies to this study not because our models
are wrong but as a reminder that all models are an
approximation and despite what i've just shown you
we are not trying to look at every individual
grain to reproduce every aspect of reality
what we are trying to do is to use numerical
models to explore complex magnetic structures
to look for general trends and
new kinds of magnetic responses
so whilst acknowledging the profound effect
of grain shape or magnetic properties
rather than looking at the very complex
shapes that i've just shown you we're
going to simplify a model and primarily what
that means looking at simpler grain shapes
and look at what we might expect the general
thermomagnetic behavior of these grains to be
and which we might expect or hope at least to
be present regardless of the exact grain shape
so one of the basic predictions of a micromagnetic
models is the critical grain size of magnetite
both transition from the single domain stabilizing
the main grain size to vortex and from vortex to
multi-domain in the results i've shown here we
modeled a magnetic grain structure as we grew a
grain from about 30 nanometers diameter
to just under 3 microns and then shrink
it back again to 30 nanometers there is some
hysteresis in the main states with grain size
which means that various green sizes cannot occupy
multiple different domain states but generally the
single main critical grain size for magnetite is
about 80 nanometers for equidimensional grains
and it's possible to nucleate a moth domain grain
like structure with well-defined block walls in
a grain perhaps as small as three microns if we
take the lower super paramagnetic to sink the main
grain size at about 40 nanometers then the grain
size range for single vortex domain structure
is about two orders of magnitude greater than
that of the single domain and of course uh the
single domain grain size range will increase
with elongation but but then of course the
single vortex range will increase also the clear
implication why i wanted to show you this is
that unless your sample has very fine grains or
small but highly elongated grains then your rock
sample is going to include many psd single board
experience and i think there is a fair chance that
the magnetization of many periodic samples will
be dominated by these single vortex domain states
so that said we are going to try and build
the single vortex model of thermo-magnetic
remnants from our micromagnetic models but
before we do that let's remind ourselves
of the assumptions of paleomagnetic recording
what we assume when a rock cools is that each
grain has a magnetic stability or relaxation
time towel which rapidly increases as the
temperature cools in fact this relaxation time
can be of the order of nanoseconds near
the temperature and of course by the time
you get to room temperature it can be many of
orders of magnitude greater than the age of the
solar system as the temperature
decreases and the relaxation time of the
of the grain approaches the observation time we
call that temperature the blocking temperature
one of the fundamental laws of paleomagnetic
observation is that for a grain that becomes
blocked at tb on cooling then on heating it
must become unblocked at that same temperature
this is the principle of reciprocity and it's
fundamental to pending magnetism because it
implies that we can replace the magnetization
lost any temperature into food in any temperature
interval as we heat up the sample with
a laboratory induced magnetization
in the same temperature interval as
we cool down and that the ratio of
the nrm loss to the peter and gained is
proportional then to the ancient field
fortunately of course this is exactly
what single domain theory predicts
uh single domain theory is shown very
briefly here it's fairly straightforward
but it's worth going through uh even
briefly since it in fact is very similar
to how we will construct our pseudo single
domain model of thermo-magnetic remnants
nael's single-domain trm theory assumes that we
have a uniaxial single-domain grain shown here so
that there are only two stable domain directions
of magnetization state one and state two either
um in along the long axis in one direction
or the other we can calculate the energy
barrier between these two states and these
energy barriers are shown here is delta
e 2 to 1 and delta e 1 to 2 depending whether
the state goes from 1 to 2 or from 2 to 1.
as from these energy bars then we can determine
the switching frequency using arrhenius's thermal
activation equation shown here is k1 to 2
k2 to 1 that describes the rate at which the
main state changes from state 1 to 2 or from
state 2 to 1. we can use these rate functions
to follow the evolution of the
domain states as a function of time
temperature and applied field in this red equation
here and we can then use that to determine the
magnetization for any temperature or time or
applied field so from these very simple set of
equations we can simulate a cooling in the field
and so calculate its thermal magnetic remnants
this single domain theory though makes
some very harsh assumptions so we
assume that all grains are uniformly magnetized
that they're uniaxial only two possible domain
states each domain state is an equal and
opposite magnetization and the energy barriers
uh assume coherent rotation of course none of
those are satisfied by single vortex screens
the predictions it makes of course are that the
trm is linearly proportional to the external field
thank goodness that the trm can be reconstructed
from uh adding a number of partial thermal
accusations that's the law of additivity
and that the single main grains block
and unblock at the same temperature
so this is the law of reciprocity
whilst we generally find of
course that the total trm
is indeed linearly proportional to the
field strength in which it's magnetized
many samples actually probably
most do not satisfy the requirement
of reciprocity of blocking temperatures so that
is illustrated here uh quite clearly this is from
data from a 2001 paper i've done up on usda
mere where they took magnetite samples of
known grain sizes and gave them a partial thermal
remnant magnetization between 350 370 and 350
and then subjected that partial thermal
remnants to a stepwise thermal demagnetization
and what they found was that between 50 and 90
of the remnants and blocks either below or above
that blocking temperature of the ptrm none of
the samples that they show here actually obey
that reciprocity law even the smallest grains
the 600 nanometers or a thousand nanometer grains
actually obey that reciprocity law so in uh pin
intensity experiments this effect would result
in a curvature of the data and the arrived plots
shown here on the right hand side with actually no
indication of whether the average gradient gives
an under or over estimate of the ancient field
so most explanations of these effects normally
call upon multi-domain behavior where we impose
a phenomenological distribution of blocking
temperatures such as the very nice work of
carl fabian and his 2000 jgi paper but although
the figures here demonstrate that reciprocity
failure increases with green size it's still
very noticeable that in the smaller screen sizes
which are clearly in the pseudoscenes of the
main grain size range also fail this reciprocity
so what i want to do in the rest of this talk uh
way behind already is to try and build a model
of pseudoscene domain trms and explore what to
what extent this can account for the reciprocity
failure that is exhibited here and to speculate
what this might then mean for our ability to
determine the ancient geomagnetic field intensity
so as in the single domain trm model to construct
our pseudo single domain thermomagnetic model
we need to find the available domain states and
calculate the energy barriers between these states
small pst grains are generally in a single
domain sorry a single vortex state as shown here
these vortex states carry their
remnants in the vortex cores
generally and they generally align with the easy
and isotropic axes either crystalline or shape
we calculate the energy barriers between the
different domain states by a technique called the
merged elastic band method that attempts to find
the minimum energy path between these two states
we can do this for all grains of all sizes for
all temperatures and then use the energy barriers
to determine the relaxation time again from the
arrhenius equation um as a function of temperature
as as as indicated here
exactly the same as we did in the single main
theory we defined the blocking temperature
where this relaxation time is equal to
the observation time and i've stated it
to arbitrarily as being 60 seconds so we
did this in our 2017 paper vers nagi and
user talks and this is what we found we found that
in fact single vortex grains were generally very
stable more than capable of carrying large
thermometic remnants of the time scales of
many billions of years we also saw that there
was an unstable zone at the transition from
the single domain grain size range to the
vortex grain size range and that as the grain
grows out of that unstable zone there is a range
of grain sizes where both hard aligned vortices
and the easy line vortices can coexist so we
speculate here and what i'm going to use in
in our model is that such grains might have
a more complex thermal magnetic response
and we're going to use an example of
such a grain to see what that might
mean in terms of a pst trm model kind
of a worst case scenario if you like
so uh this is the grain that we're going to
concentrate on first this uh talk it's a 100
nanometer cube octahedral grain 30 elongated
along the 100 direction and it has several
blocking temperatures but the major blocking
temperature is about 200 degrees centigrade or so
so it can nucleate a stable vortex domain
structure along the one zero zero or minus
one zero zero direction that's along the long
axis of the grain and there are four other
stable vortex states along the short axis
and there are four symmetrical short axes
as shown here the zero one one uh well you
can read them i'm not going to read them out
and the lem energies of each of these domain
states are pretty much identical for all
temperatures so here's a the energies
as a function of temperature of course
people say well of course this is dominated by
ms and we should normalize it by ms which i've
tried it doesn't really help very much
so uh they're almost equal you can see
a change in fact for uh for the lowest
energy domain state that transits from
the short axis the short axis at room temperatures
lowest energy domain state and the long axis is
slightly higher this changes at a temperature of
160 degrees where for a long period afterwards the
long axis is the lowest energy state and
the short axis are is the high energy state
so we are going to construct a thermal
activation model for single vortex grains
and we in order to do that we need to calculate
the relaxation frequencies given by this equation
between every available domain state and
in an applied field h this means we need
to calculate the energy barriers between
each short axis and every other short axis
should align states and between each long axis
aligned state and every other short axis state
all these possible transitions are shown here in
this central figure but as we will see on the next
slide these are in fact just a combination of a
very few different types of the main transitions
from the relaxation times you build a complete
matrix here of relaxation frequencies between
all the different domain states here labeled
this q matrix and from this we can determine
the relative population of the different domain
states at a particular temperature and time using
the matrix exponential and a method outlined by
fabian and shishobikov in their jgi 218 paper
we can then evolve this system through an
innovative process where the population of
different domain states at a time t plus delta
t is simply given by the population of the
of the domain states at a time t multiplied
by the matrix of transition probabilities
since the time and field can change
with sorry since the temperature and
field can change with time it can evolve
the system through any arbitrary sequence
of thermal history and in particular we
can simulate the acquisition of an nrm
plus its subsequent thermal cycling through a
multi-step talia type pill intensity experiment
and so we're now going to
look at some of those results
so the matrix of translation frequencies we saw
on the previous slide as i said was made up of a
number of different symmetrical domain transitions
that can be one of three types we can have
transitions between a short axis and a long
axis or a short axis and another short axis
or a long axis and a short axis every other domain
state that you see in this grain can be achieved
through a hop between one of those different
types of transitions so the short line axis
the shorter line vortex to the longer line
vortex transition curve is given by this red line
the long aligned vortex to the shorter line
vortex transition is given by the blue line
and the short line vortex to this nearest other
short line vortex is given by this green line so
the three transitions that are possible in this
particular grain the other thing that's important
to realize at this point is that the domain
states have uh different net magnetizations
so that the magnetization along let me go back
once i missed one uh the magnetization these are
the magnetizations as a function of temperature
for each of the uh for the long and the short
axis aligned vortex state and you can see uh what
this is negative here but you can see that the
long aligned vortex state has a much
larger magnetization than the short and
basic the remnants is carried by the core
the vortex core is longer in the long axis
than it is in the short and so it
yields a higher magnetic remnants
by about 44
so this relaxation phase diagram is
very important because it actually
defines the complete thermometic behavior of
the grain and so it's worth looking at in some
detail in the yellow region here for temperatures
above about 240 centigrade the only stable state
on normal time scales is the vortex state aligned
along the long axis so the stability of the state
is given by the height above a any
particular relaxation type so if we take
grains that are stable on time scales of
longer than one minute we can see that
nothing is stable above about 500 degrees
but then the long aligned axis becomes stable
so anything that gets into the long axis there's
an energy barrier between that and the short axis
at the other extreme at lower temperatures
up to about 130 degrees centigrade it's green
shaded region all the main states are stable
and in fact the energy barriers in all these
states are so high that's going to be almost
impossible to change from one state to the other
this blue shaded region is the
critical zone and this is where the
rate at which the sample is cooled through this
zone dramatically affects the room temperature
distribution of the blocked domain states
uh okay and way over time already so i'll try and
speed up so we take two particular examples here
fast and slow cooling so this is an example of
fast cooling uh shown by this dotted line here
and virtually all the main states sorry the first
domain state to be blocked this week as we cool
from high temperatures is the long aligned domain
states and by the time any other domain state
becomes possible this energy barrier is too high
so we reach room temperature everything is aligned
along the long axis we can take another example of
fast cooling of sorry slow cooling shown by this
relaxation time of a million years a very extreme
case and as we see here as we cool down the first
domain state to become stable is the barrier
between the short and the long so everything
likes to be aligned along the short axis and as
you could it further when in fact the long axis
here never becomes stable so in very slow slowly
cooled samples everything is going to be aligned
along the short axis in very fast cooled samples
everything will be aligned along the long axis
so this is completely counter intuitive and
opposite to the cooling rate correction i guess
we we common we think of in single main grains
and of course this is just one grain i'm not
suggesting this is true for all pseudosynthetic
membranes or even also the vortex domain states
but it's a clear demonstration that even in
this rather common grain morphology these
unexpected magnetic facts can happen and it might
well be common enough to account for the observed
ptrm tails and curvature and they observed
their eye plots it's also illustrative of this
previously undocumented effect in psd grains of
a temperature and thermal history dependence of
magnetic domain structure that controls
the preferred alignment of domain states
the next step is to continue around to consider
a random distribution of such particles and
simulate the thermal cycling an italian
multi-step type paleo intensity experiment
that involves cooling from above the curio
parent to generate an nrm and i will show you
a couple of examples at different cooling rates
and then thermal cycling in a in a multi-step
tele experiment which we use a laboratory
cooling rate of 40 minutes per temperature step
uh one of the first things to check of course
is that our nrm is linearly proportional to the
applied field so that's what i show here on the
left hand side on the right hand side here is the
sequence of temperature and fields as a function
of time in our simulated multi-step turian
experiment this is just one protocol actually
the simulations i'll show you will have ptrm
checks in it and ptm tail checks in it as well
so here's the first simulated arrive plot it's
for a slowly cooled nrm over 600 million seconds
so that's about 18 years and as already said
the laboratory cooling rate of 40 minutes
this slow cooling has resulted in domain states
predominantly aligned on the short grain axis
and the fast laboratory remagnetization realigns
the magnetization to the long axis so the large
difference in the re-magnetization occupancy
of states results in this very large ptrm check
failures shown by these red triangles here and
of course these ptrm failures are intrinsic to
the domain structure of course are nothing
to do with chemical alteration and although
not often done the ptrm tail check shown
here by this green rectangle is also very
large and this is an indication of the failure
of the reciprocity of the blocking temperatures
if we look at a cooling rate
much closer to the lobarte rate
this one is cooled over 6 000 seconds so that's
about uh that's about 1.7 hours we see that
the sample now passes the ptrm check from these
red triangles but still fails the ptrm tail check
and the blocking temperature reciprocity
failure indicated by the tail check at 175
degrees centigrade then contributes
to the curvature of the arrive plot
so one thing i would like to explain if i just
have a few more minutes is the both the arri plots
exhibit high temperature ptrm hooks shown
by this green region caused by a peak in
the ptm gained between two and 300 degrees
centigrade and a decrease at high temperatures
subsequently shown by this yellow region the
magnetization plot and this can be explained
by examining our relaxation phase diagram as
we put in ptrms at increasing temperatures
we first activate the grains that are aligned
on the short axis as we as we heat up from
below the first grains that we reactivate
that become unstable are the short-lined
grains and then these grains will transit to
long aligned axes which have larger remnancies
and so we get an increase in the ptrm peak at
around two to three once we get into regions
where the long axis grains can be reactivated
then some of those long axis grains will
switch to short axes and then we get this
decrease of the ptram at large ptrm temperatures
so in this instance then this uh
difference in blocking temperature
from heating from below or cooling from
above explains the reciprocity failure
and this decrease in the as i said decrease
in the ptrm for increasing temperatures then
explains this hook that we
see at high temperatures
so these features of high temperature hooks
and peaks in the high temperature ptrms
are not so unusual and i've got one
example here from a sample of a larva
from ohio basaltic lava from hawaii that shows the
same high temperature ptrm hook of course this is
just one example uh there may be many explorations
for such magnetic behavior but it's likely that
these fine-grained vessels actually do contain psd
grains and at least it is consistent with the uh
observations and predictions that we make all
right so i've made uh i've covered a lot of ground
uh gone way over time which i apologize for i'm
just going to summarize the results in four short
slides so we've built a thermomagnetic model for
psd grains that accounts for any thermal magnetic
history it predicts this failure of reciprocity so
the blocking and unblocking temperatures are quite
different that results in ptrm check failures
can result in petrium tails uh it rises when
different domain states with similar energy
barriers are possible in one particular grain
this is unlike multi-domain grains
though because the domain states
have high remnancies the number of domain states
are fewer and behave in a more predictable way
the very large ptrm failure and ptm tails in our
example are the result of large differences in
the remnants of the different allowed domain
states and the fact that the energy barriers
between the different domain states change as
at different rates as a function of temperature
extreme reciprocity failure shown in our example
um is uh sorry the extreme reciprocity failure
shown in our example are seen in single vortex
grains that have multiplicity of different
domain states i think that i've already said
which may be predictable and you might argue
that that actually the number of grains that have
this multiplicity of the main state is actually
very narrow and larger grains are going to be
slightly better behaved maybe predominantly
vortices aligned with the easy axis however
in real grains of course you have lots of
highly irregular grain shapes as i showed at the
beginning of the talk with multiple grain axes
that might in fact then promote the existence of
multiple lem states even in these small grains
and so might have benefit from the same
effects that we've shown in this example today
so we know that these combined effects
whatever the grain sizes range and whatever
grains shapes are affected by the things that
i've shown today these cannot be so big that they
completely destroy paleomagnetism because we know
we can extract failure intensities sometimes and
the exciting advance that we've shown today is
that actually can now simulate trms in single
boarding grains we do still need to map out the
relaxation phase diagrams for different grain
sizes and shapes and to look at how big an effect
this might be which grains are poor recorders
and how maybe we can detect them
and finally we hope les and i hope
together that we're going to build a compact
and easily run simulation tool for mixtures of
single domain and psd grains to explore these
types of magnetic recording characteristics
okay it was only roughly twice the time i think so
thanks very much you're all only at five minutes
over so i think we can uh i'll give when a a round
of applause for a really interesting talk with
a lot of a lot of profound implications i think
for how we understand uh paleomagnetism and
paleomagnetic recorders so um i can open the
floor to to to questions so you please feel free
to raise your hand uh gilder is straight in there
and you go sure so thanks for that but i i have
a question i don't understand why cooling rate
is going to influence which access gets
gets magnetized or why it's going to
yeah by that would influence but but my more my my
really important question there is i would imagine
that which axis gets magnetized depends on
field strength so does it depend on field
yeah it of course it does the field strength uh
the field strength produces a bias but you know
we had a random assembly of such grains so uh
the component of the field uh might equally
be aligned along some short axes or long axis
so the field produces a bias to alignment
of the domain states whether they're
along the short or the long so that doesn't uh you
know if we had if we had every grain was aligned
the particular anisotropy and all the
grains were aligned in terms of their shape
then that might be the effect but we have these
are random completely random distributions so um
and in fact i mean i haven't shown you know
try to squeeze in as much as i could today
you can look at the zydefelt plots and
they they perfectly well record paleo
in paleomagnetic directions uh so um there's
no fabric if you like in these in terms of the
cooling rate so your question was that
the ability of cooling rate to change the
preference of the alignment of the grains i
obviously didn't explain that well enough i
rushed too much i i can go through it very quickly
again uh possibly if i can get back go back from
slide 160 to okay let's take the first one here
so the the cooling rate dependence uh really is
embedded in this phase diagram of the main states
because it depends upon as you cool down which um
which type of domain state nucleates
first and becomes stable first
you know so at very high temperatures you
can see all these relaxation times are very
very small so below about 500 everything is
really tiny and everything is unstable as we
as we might expect and at fast cooling rates so
we can imagine that each of these temperatures are
only only sits at each of these temperatures
for one minute i mean obviously in our in our
simulations of nrm we have a newtonian cooling
rate but just a very brutal approximation here
if we t imagine each of these temperatures that
sits at for one minute then we might we might
get the domain states that are indicated where
this relaxation time creates uh energy barrier
with the domain states so as you cool down um
the the first energy barrier for fast cooling
i'm calling one minute at each temperature fast
cooling the first domain state energy barrier
is defined by the transition from the long to
the short so any grains that end up being the
long aligned along the long axis can't easily
move to the short axis and but the time that
the short axis remain is available as a stable
if you like so that's below about 200 degrees
so here we find a shorter long energy barrier so
these are now stable the short axis is no stable
but the problem is that everything
is already locked in the long axis
so so that's what happens at fast cooling
rates a very long cooling rates then everything
is essentially uh unstable on the million
year time scale until you get down to
whatever this is 140 or 130 degrees and
the first energy barrier that it comes
that it comes across the first thing that
becomes stable are the shorter line grains
so anything that finds itself in a short aligned
axis can't easily move out into anything else
and the longer line actually doesn't become
stable until about room temperature so
uh that's an extreme example i mean not many
things look cool at time scales of millions of
years but it's extreme example but this the exact
position of these different relaxation curves
essentially defines how the proportion or the
proportion of the domain states are distributed
among the different available domain states
depending how quickly they move through this
this is decision point if you like of
the different uh domain state frequencies
did that make any sense cheese dude
yeah and so those curves are made
with large numbers of grains that are
randomly oriented is that these domain
these energy barriers refer to just one
orientation so uh these are the these
are the different allowed domain states
so this this doesn't have any field um
these energy barriers assume no external field
we add that into the model uh in this other
part here so that was just the three different
types of transitions we can have short to long
long to short short to short in terms of the
orientation of the domains with respect to the
grain axes and then so that's and the
different types of transitions are shown here
so this is uh this is one particular short
axis so there are four different short axes
and two different long axes and you can look at
all the different transitions of every grain with
every one you don't have anti-parallel transitions
because they always go very different different
domain state but all of these combination of
different transitions are incorporated in this
relaxation frequency matrix and that includes
a bias to the field which is a vector
when we look at our district random distribution
of grains of course then we in each orientation
of that grain we'll see it essentially a
different direction of the magnetic field
relative to the green axes okay it's the algebra
is a bit messy but that's the part i missed
yeah thank you yeah thank you very much uh
brandon has his hand up as well for a question
hi hi brandon um yeah uh i had a question what
size is the grain that you're showing here
with the rf block so the grain this one uh these
arrive plots are for a mono dispersion so they are
100 nanometers uh we use this hundred nanometers
esvd uh we always like to code things in terms of
svds which is the equivalent spherical
volume diameter anyways hundred nanometers
thirty percent elongated along the um
one zero zero axes and um it was chosen
because it was just on the boundary as
you emerge from this unstable zone that we
predict uh from this from our 2017 paper we chose
it because we didn't know actually uh how it is
going to behave thermometically and we wanted to
look for something that was likely to have a large
effect uh in the end it has a very large effect
much more than we probably um would have liked but
um the the principle here is that we
have a grain that has a mud that has
different domain states of similar energies in
it i think that's the principle so this effect
although we've we've chosen it because we knew it
was going to have two different domain states that
were stable in it i think it this the effects that
we see should be replicated in any grain that has
different domain states of similar energies
in it if you have a dominant if you have a
a minimum energy state that is uh much lower
than other possible domain states through
out its temperature range then
you won't see these effects
so the question is how frequent are these
types of domain or grains and as i said we
people have got pale intensities including you
that we think are reasonably good and but you know
we all know that it's not unusual to have
pain intensity failure rates high percentages
many of those are chemical alteration sometimes
chemical alteration is indicated by these ptrm
failures we can we've shown here that ptm failures
don't have to be because of chemical operation
uh but the extent to which this can
account for uh the curvature for instance
in the arrive plots is something that we
hope to determine over the next few years
yeah have you tried this at any other sizes yet
or you've just got we uh we want to publish this
because i'm terrible at publishing i can see
we'll be smiling when i say that okay but we're
going to publish this soon and then we're
going to move on to the other domain states
now we you know these what i'm really
uh pleased with is these um these
uh energy barriers as a function of temperature
these are not polynomial fits these are actually
individual points of the energy barriers that
we've calculated uh you know to calculate
so we parameterize these in terms of
polynomials it makes our simulations of of uh
simulations of thermomagnetic histories much
quicker and easier to do and what we'd like
to do is suggest is to parametrize a whole
bunch of these things which is pretty much
donkey work but it needs to be done over the next
few months and then produce this nice tool where
we can have a simulation of mixtures of single
domain and psd uranes non-interactive of course
thank you very much brendan um we've got time for
one quick more question for when before we there
we go there's the inevitable question from rich
harrison marriage again yeah this is great win um
yeah so i mean how this is going to develop is i
mean ultimately what we'd like to be able to do
is once you've done all that that sort of what
what did you call it donkey work or yeah grand
creation to be able to map what you find in the
what you showed at the beginning which is the sort
of slice and view models right where you have you
have your particle size distribution and you know
that in great detail to be able to map that onto
this model and then and then do the calculation
to compare it to an actual real sample so so how
far away from that that dream are we i think we
are well um you're a potential reviewer richard
so uh if we get the grand proposal it'll take
about 12 months after that it's one of these new
fancy new proposals um but uh i asked a bit uh
to get a whole bunch of these done we have a we
have a workflow now which is which produces these
incredibly nice uh there's a bit noisy at high
temperatures but very smooth um energy bars as
a function of temperature we have a workflow
that allows us to do that pretty easily so
we're hoping to get to get this done within uh 12
months that's some yeah that's what we're hoping
and i guess you have to look closely with like a
really broad range of particle sizes and shapes
as possible so we would the aim
is to do uh to to do grain sizes
from from the sort of paramagnetic green size up
to about probably a limit is going to be about
200 to say 250 nanometers and elongations from
eco-dimensional up to maybe 500 elongation
that's our hope in fact all the numerical all the
micromagnetic models themselves have been done
we just need to do the groundwater processing
so yeah hopefully so thank you very much for the
questions um i think we'll we'll uh draw today's
seminar to a close but i want to ask everybody
to give uh another uh round of applause for
for a really good talk thank you very much gwen
thank you and i will just hijack the screen share
so um there we go so i i've updated your
title i've got it correct this time when
i noticed you kind of avoided that
question of actually how well can we
uh know the entrance your magnetic
field maybe in the next magnet seminar
uh your answer to that question is
going to be very well in a year's time
and so just before uh we bring it all to
a complete end um just a reminder that
um we're gonna have a short break for
uh egu and then we'll come back um in in
uh mid-june um but we're moving to an eu eastern
hemisphere uh time slot so our seminars will be
in the mornings in in europe and there'll be sort
of late afternoons into the evenings uh in in the
eastern hemisphere depending upon where you are um
and so uh there'll be more announcements about the
exact timing of that and so we've got a couple of
speakers lined up already uh and we have some more
uh in in in plans but as always we're looking for
uh more speakers um for our seminar so if anybody
is interested in giving a seminar uh please
just um let us know and all of our seminars
including the recording for uh winstop today
will be made available on our youtube channel
and so thank you everybody for joining magnets
and we'll see you next month thank you very much